INSTRUCTOR: Hello, everyone,
and welcome to the content video
for List versus BST.
OK, so here, I just put
together a little bit of code
to compare which one's really
faster, a list versus a BST?
So let's take a look at that.
It's actually inside
the code bst.py,
although you'll need all of
the functions for the BST,
you'll need completed.
So really, check out--
if you want to go
straight to the solution,
check out bst_complete.py,
although I highly recommend
to try and do the programming
activities inside bst.py
yourself to make sure that
you understand and can do them
yourself.
But let's take a look here.
So we have BST_complete.
OK, so check out line 225 right
here that I'm highlighting.
Here, I'm creating a list
of a million random numbers.
And all of the numbers
themselves are between 1
and 10,000.
So between 1 and 10,000, and
there's a million of those.
All right, then I'm going to
search for the numbers between 1
and 10,000 inside there.
So it has to go through the
list of a million numbers
until it finds that specific
number I'm looking for.
So what order of
complexity is this?
Well, for all the
numbers, it's order n
squared, but for each
individual number, it's order n.
Check out lines 231 to 233.
So I'm just looping
through the list
until I finally find the
number, then I break.
OK, so I look for those
numbers 10,000 times,
order n 10,000 times, and then
I keep track of how long that
took.
And here I'm using the
time.time function.
Have an end1 minus start1.
That will tell me
how long it took.
OK, now I'm going to
do the same thing,
but I'm going to
do it in a tree.
So check out lines 240 here.
I have a root, which
is equal to my insert.
And then I insert the root and
then a random number between 1
and 10,000.
And I do that one million times.
So when I'm done
here, I'll have a list
of a million random
numbers and a tree
of a million random numbers.
Then I'm going to search
the tree using findKey.
It'll just go looking through
my binary search tree.
And then let's see
which one is faster.
OK, so it's running
right now for the list.
And it just finished
for the list.
So let's look at that
output right here.
So if you can see where I'm
highlighting in my console,
it took 3.12 seconds to build
the list of a million random
numbers and then search it
10,000 times for the random
numbers that's looking for.
So then why isn't the tree done?
Why isn't-- aren't trees
supposed to be way more faster?
So here's what's going on.
Here's why the tree
one is not done yet.
The finds are actually
extremely fast,
but building the tree,
recursing through it
over and over and over again,
is what's taking longer.
So the building
the tree is longer,
but the searching it, as you'll
see as soon as it finishes,
is much faster.
And there it is.
So how long did it take it
to search 10,000 numbers?
Less than a second,
4/100 of a second.
So how much faster is 4/100
of a second versus three full
seconds?
Not quite a-- not quite
an order of magnitude
of 100, but much,
much, much faster.
So the finds were
definitely faster,
but it took a little bit longer
to build the tree itself.
So then if you're
thinking, well,
how do I know then
which one to use when?
I would say if you have to--
if your application requires
you to rebuild your data
set over and over and
over and over and over,
then maybe a list, or
honestly, probably, you're
better off using a NumPy Array
because the underlying data
types will be in C,
that'll be faster.
But I would recommend a NumPy
Array or a Pandas DataFrame.
But what if you're
building something
where you're adding
to it over and over
and over again, like
an index in a database
or the nodes in a
network you're building?
You're just adding
more and more and more.
Then I would definitely say a
list because the find, insert,
and deletes are
going to be quicker.
So there you go.
You can see tree definitely
won in finding it,
but it took longer to build.
So is there one final answer
for when to use this data
structure always?
It depends.
It depends on your application
and what exactly you're doing.
But tree is a very useful one.
It gets you order log
n time and is fast.
OK, so there is our content
video for list versus trees,
in this case, a binary
search tree in Python.
Thanks so much for watching.